RG 024, Historical Commission
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut Historical Commission records
1768-1987
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut Historical Commission
13.75 cubic feet
The Connecticut Historical Commission performed a variety of functions having to do with the preservation of historic sites and structures and other historical resources.
RG024
Multiple
Historical Note
The State Historical Commission was established by statute in 1955 to perform a variety of functions having to do with the preservation of historic sites and structures and other historical resources. It administered several historic properties including the Henry Whitfield House in Guilford. This building is said to be the oldest stone house in Connecticut, built in 1639. From 1900, when it was purchased by the State, it was administered (and known as the "State Historical Museum") by an appointed Board of Trustees. In 1973, the General Assembly acted to place it under the jurisdiction of the Historical Commission. The Commission also served as the American Revolution Bicentennial Commission of Connecticut. The Commission also oversaw the State Historic Resources Inventory which begun in Connecticut in 1974. In 2003, the Historical Commission merged into the new Commission on Arts, Tourism, Culture, History and Film.
See also the.
Scope and Content
The records of the Connecticut Historical Commission are divided into one subgroup and three series. Subgroup one contains correspondence, reports, and other documentation on the restoration of the Henry Whitfield House, a State Historical Museum in Guilford, together with deeds and other papers on Guilford families. The second series relates to the American Revolution Bicentennial Commission of Connecticut, which lasted from 1974-1978, and documentation includes subject files, clippings, and scrapbooks. The third series contain a small volume of resolutions expressing gratitude, sorrow and respect, or other form of acknowledgement for members and citizens. Finally, there are six boxes of microfiche on the Connecticut Historical Commission’s Statewide Historic Resources Inventory.
Arrangement
Subgroup 1. Henry Whitfield House, 1768-1957, Accession: 1958-002, 2 cubic feet.
Series 2. The Connecticut American Revolution Bicentennial Commission, 1973-1978, 10.5 cubic feet
Accession: T000562, 3 cubic feet
Accession: T000549, 7.5 cubic feet
Series 3. Resolutions, 1982-1986, Accession: T000549, 1 large envelope.
Series 4-9. Not used.
Series 10. Statewide Historic Resource Directory, circa 1974-1987, Accession: T000547, 1.25 cubic feet (6 microfiche clamshell boxes).
Related Material
RG 033, Works Progress Administration, HABS Survey
RG 143, Old Houses of Connecticut, collected and compiled by the Connecticut Society of Colonial Dames of America.
PG 600, Additional Bicentennial posters.
Donohue, Mary M. and David A. Poirier. "The Connecticut Historic Preservation Collection: An Introduction to the State's Archaeological and Architectural Reocrds." Bulletin of the Archaeological Society of Connecticut 48 (1985): 13-30.
Poirier, David A. Historic preservation: A User's Guide to the Connecticut Historic Preservation Collection. Hartford, Conn.: Connecticut Historical Commission, 1991
. [H65 hpre].
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut Historical Commission; American Revolution Bicentennial Commission of Connecticut; Trustees of the Henry Whitfield House
Subjects:
American Revolution Bicentennial, 1776-1976 -- Connecticut; American Revolution Bicentennial Commission of Connecticut -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut Historical Commission -- Records and correspondence; Henry Whitfield House (Guilford, Conn.); Henry Whitfield State Museum (Conn.); Historic buildings -- Connecticut; Historic preservation -- Connecticut; Historic sites -- Connecticut; United States -- Centennial celebrations, etc. -- Connecticut; National Society of the Colonial Dames of America in the State of Connecticut
Document Types:
Blueprints; Broadsides; Clippings; Correspondence; Deeds; Drawings; Lists; Memorabilia; Microfiche; Pamphlets; Photographs; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Subgroup 1. Henry Whitfield House, 1768-1957
  Inventory of Henry Whitfield House Records
- Series 2. The Connecticut American Revolution Bicentennial Commission, 1973-1978; 10.5 cubic feet
  - Bicentennial Commission papers, 1973-1978
    Correspondence, memoranda and related materials pertaining to the administration and the work of the American Revolution Bicentennial Commission of Connecticut.
    - T000562, 3 cubic feet
      - Annual report, statutes, etc., 1 binder and 1 folder (1 inch) (Box 1)
      - Office calendars, 1974 September - 1978 April; 1 folder (1 inch) (Box 1)
        Showing appointments and festivities.
      - Press releases, 1974-1976; 2 folders (1 inch) (Box 1)
      - Draft "Bicentennial History of Connecticut's Role in the American Revolution together with the Actions of the General Assembly," by Robert S. Orcutt, 1 folder (1 1/2 inches) (Box 1)
      - "Bicentennial Gazette" printing file, 1976-1977; 1 folder (1/2 inch) (Box 1)
      - Subject file, 1974-1978; 23 folders (5 inches) (Box 2)
        Correspondence with manufacturers and vendors of promotional items.
        Aphabetical by subject.
        - Balloon, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Belt buckles (Box 2)
        - Benhaven buttons (Box 2)
        - Billboard (Box 2)
        - Bumper stickers and decals (Box 2)
        - Displays (Box 2)
        - Filmstrip (Box 2)
        - The Flag Store (Box 2)
        - Lapel pins (Box 2)
        - Map, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Medalic Art (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
        - Pewter Plate (Box 2)
        - Place mats (Box 2)
        - Plaques (INEMCO) (Box 2)
        - St. Eustatius, N.A. (Box 2)
        - Shoulder patches (Box 2)
        - Connecticut Historic Houses (sketchbook) (Box 2)
        - Soldier prints (Box 2)
        - T-Shirts (Box 2)
        - Typesetting bid (Box 2)
      - Schools program material, 1975-1976; 1 folder (1 inch) (Box 3)
      - American Association for State and Local History award applications, 13 folders (4 inches) (Box 3)
      - "A program for the Connecticut Museum," by Daniel R. Porter, 1 binder (1 inch) (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous and unfiled materials, 4 inches (Box 4)
        Including correspondence, unanswered letters, press releases, clipings, list of towns applying for grants, checklist of town committees (1977 October), list of promotional items, etc.
      - Drawings and sketches of bicentennial activities in Mansfield, the Oldfield School (Fairfield), Damascus Elementary School (Branford) and Bullard-Havens Technical School, 1 folder (3 inches) (Box 5 + oversize loose items)
      - Clippings and scrapbooks pertaining to bicentennial activities, 1973-1977 (Box 5)
    - T000549, 7.5 cubic feet
      - Clippings and scrapbooks pertaining to bicentennial activities., 1973-1977; 4 large binders (Volume Item 6-9)
      - Layouts, sketches, drawings, paste-ups and other preliminary materials for publications, 1 oversize flat box (Box 10 + oversize loose items)
  - Bicentennial Commission broadsides, pamphlets, publications, and other memorabilla, 1974-1977; T000549; 1 oversize flat box (Box 11)
    - Calendar of Connecticut Bicentennial Events, 23 items in large envelope (Box 11)
      - 1976 March, 2 copies (Box 11)
      - 1976 April, 2 copies (Box 11)
      - May (Box 11)
      - 1976 June (Box 11)
      - 1976 July (Box 11)
      - 1976 August (Box 11)
      - 1976 November, 2 copies (Box 11)
      - 1976 December (Box 11)
      - April 16-26 (Box 11)
      - June 1-30 (Box 11)
      - July 1-31 (Box 11)
      - November 1-30 (Box 11)
      - December 1-31 (Box 11)
      - July (Box 11)
      - A State of Courage, 1 broadside (Box 11)
      - A State of Heroism - Colonel Thomas Knowlton, 1 broadside (Box 11)
      - A State of Heroism - Nathan Hale, 1 broadside (Box 11)
      - A State of Liberation - Ella Grasso, 1 broadside (Box 11)
      - A State of Style: Fashions and Accessories of the Revolutionary Era, 1 broadside (Box 11)
    - Connecticut Courant, 1764 October 29 (Box 11)
    - Connecticut the Provision State, 1 small broadside (Box 11)
    - East Hartford Bicentennial Commission (Box 11)
      - Invitation to attend Connecticut premiere of motion picture, "These States", 1975 April, 16 (Box 11)
      - Description of film, broadside - 2 copies; 1 autographed (Box 11)
    - Fales, Edward, Jr., ed. Arsenal of the Revolution: The First History of "The 14th Colony." A pulbication of the Lakeville Journal and the News (Box 11)
    - The Hartford Courant, sponsor. The United States Armed Forces Bicentennial Band, 1975 April 17; 1 broadside (Box 11)
      Concert.
    - Old Lyme Bicentennial Commission (Box 11)
      - Nathan Hale Fifes & Drums and Knowlton's rangers coming to Old Lyme High School Field, July 12, August 30; 2 broadsides (Box 11)
      - "The Pursuit of Happiness." Old Lyme High School, July 4, 5-11, 12; 1 broadside (Box 11)
        Revolutionary War play.
    - "Adventures along the Connecticut Coast." Vocal by Re Circo. (On other side "Morning after Dreamer." Vocal by Re Circo), 1 record (Box 11)
    - The Symbol of the Bicentennial Council of the Thirteen Original States, 1 broadside (Box 11)
    - Voluntown Historical Society: Map of Voluntown (Bicentennial project), 1975 (Box 11)
      Includes directory of businesses, farms, historical places, etc.
    - Miscellaneous printed pamphlets and publications (Box 11)
      Arranged by title.
      - Bicentennial celebration ye citizens of East Hartford. American Revolution Bicentennial Commission of East Hartford, Connecticut (Box 11)
      - The Bicentennial Commemoration of the Battle of Compo. Presented by the Bicentennial Committee of Westport, Connecticut, 1977 May 7 (Box 11)
      - The Bicentennial in Connecticut. American Revolution Bicentennial Commission of Connecticut (Box 11)
      - Connectiuct Bicentennial Events, 2 items (Box 11)
        - Summer 1976 (Box 11)
        - 1976 August-December (Box 11)
      - A Connecticut Historical Tour. Mystic Seaport (Box 11)
      - Connecticut So Much So Near. Points of Interest. Bicentennial Edition (Box 11)
      - Connecticut the Provision State. Teacher's Guide (Box 11)
      - The East Haven Bicentennial Commission (Box 11)
        List of items placed in capsule December 19, 1976. Capsule buried in front lawn of East Haven Town Hall.
      - If I were a Girl Scout in 1776 (Box 11)
        1776 Badge Handbook.
      - Let Freedom Ring (Box 11)
        Commemorating the Bicentennial of American Independence.
      - Nathan Hale (Box 11)
        Postcard issued by Antiquarian & Landmarks Society, Inc. of Connecticut.
      - New Haven Newsletter (Box 11)
      - New Haven Newsletter. American Revolution Bicentennial Commission., 2 items (Box 11)
        - Volume 1, No. 4, Fall 1974 (Box 11)
        - Volume 2, No. 1, Winter 1975 (Box 11)
      - Old New-Gate Prison and Copper Mine, East Granby, Connecticut (Box 11)
      - Preparing for '76: Connecticut Libraries and the Bicentennial Celebration, 1975 January 15, 1975 January 30 (Box 11)
        The Connecticut Library Association Mid-Winter Regional Meetings.
      - Town Meeting '76 (Box 11)
      - What You Can Do: A Bicentennial Idea Book (Box 11)
      - Yesterday is alive and well and living in Old Wethersfield, Connecticut at Silas Dean's House, Webb House and the Isaac Stevens House (Box 11)
    - Commemorative broadsides, 4 folders (Volume Oversize items)
      - Towns, 1 folder
      - Connecticut, 1 folder
      - States, 1 folder
      - National, 1 folder
- Series 3. Resolutions, 1982-1986; T000549; 1 large envelope
  Resolutions expressing gratitude, sorrow and respect, or other form of acknowledgement for members and citizens.
  - Resolutions, 1982-1986 (Box 11)
- Series 4-9. Not used.
- Series 10. Statewide Historic Resource Directory, circa 1974-1987; T000547; 1.25 cubic feet (6 microfiche clamshell boxes)
  Microfiche of State Historic Resource Inventory.
  Organized alphabetically by town.
  - Andover, 3 sheets (Box 12)
  - Ansonia, 3 sheets (Box 12)
  - Ashford, 3 sheets (Box 12)
  - Barkhamsted, 3 sheets (Box 12)
  - Bolton, 2 sheets (Box 12)
  - Branford, 11 sheets (Box 12)
  - Bridgeport, 16 sheets (Box 12)
  - Bridgeport (East Main St.), 2 sheets (Box 12)
  - Bridgeport (Stratfield), 11 sheets (Box 12)
  - Bridgeport (Washington Park), 3 sheets (Box 12)
  - Bristol, 18 sheets (Box 12)
  - Brooklyn, 5 sheets (Box 12)
  - Canterbury, 5 sheets (Box 12)
  - Canton, 7 sheets (2 sets) (Box 12)
  - Chaplin, 3 sheets (Box 12)
  - Chester, 11 sheets (Box 12)
  - Clinton, 11 sheets (Box 12)
  - Columbia, 3 sheets (Box 12)
  - Coventry, 8 sheets (Box 12)
  - Cromwell, 2 sheets (Box 12)
  - Danbury, 21 sheets (Box 12)
  - Darien, 14 sheets (Box 13)
  - Deep River, 5 sheets (Box 13)
  - Derby, 6 sheets (Box 13)
  - Eastford, 8 sheets (Box 13)
  - Eastford, 8 sheets (2 sets) (Box 13)
  - East Haddam, 15 sheets (Box 13)
  - East Hampton, 6 sheets (Box 13)
  - East Hartford, 8 sheets (Box 13)
  - East Hartford, 12 sheets (Box 13)
  - East Hartford (Phase 3), 13 sheets (Box 13)
  - Essex, 19 sheets (Box 13)
  - Farmington, 18 sheets (Box 13)
  - Goshen, 1 sheet (2 sets) (Box 13)
  - Greenwich (Central), 5 sheets (Box 13)
  - Guilford, 13 sheets (Box 13)
  - Haddam, 12 sheets (Box 13)
  - Hampton, 4 sheets (Box 13)
  - Hartford, 4 sheets (Box 13)
  - Harwinton, 1 sheet (Box 13)
  - Hebron, 6 sheets (Box 13)
  - Killingly, 10 sheets (Box 14)
  - Killingworth, 7 sheets (Box 14)
  - Lebanon, 11 sheets (Box 14)
  - Litchfield (Milton area), 3 sheets (Box 14)
  - Lyme, 5 sheets (Box 14)
  - Madison, 9 sheets (Box 14)
  - Manchester (Expansion Area), 1981; 19 sheets (Box 14)
  - Manchester (Reconnaissance-level), 14 sheets (Box 14)
  - Mansfield (University of Connecticut residences), 2 sheets (Box 14)
  - Marlborough, 3 sheets (Box 14)
  - Meriden, 11 sheets (Box 14)
  - Middlefield, 3 sheets (Box 14)
  - Milford, 8 sheets (Box 14)
  - Morris, 3 sheets (Box 14)
  - New Britain, 4 sheets (Box 14)
  - New Britain (Central Business District), 5 sheets (Box 14)
  - New Hartford, 3 sheets (Box 14)
  - New Haven (Central), 33 sheets (Box 14)
  - New London (Completion Survey), 21 sheets (Box 15)
  - New London (Downtown), 33 sheets (Box 15)
  - New London (Green Harbor), 11 sheets (Box 15)
  - New London (Pequot Colony), 11 sheets (Box 15)
  - New London (Reconnaissance), 11 sheets (Box 15)
  - New Milford, 5 sheets (Box 15)
  - Norfolk, 3 sheets (Box 15)
  - North Branford, 8 sheets (Box 15)
  - North Haven, 6 sheets (Box 15)
  - Norwalk, 19 sheets (Box 15)
  - Norwich (Jail Hill), 10 sheets (Box 15)
  - Norwich (Preservation Plan-facade design), 3 sheets (Box 15)
  - Norwich (Reconnaissance), 15 sheets (Box 15)
  - Plainfield, 5 sheets (Box 15)
  - Plainville, 11 sheets (Box 15)
  - Portland, 6 sheets (Box 16)
  - Putnam, 8 sheets (Box 16)
  - Simsbury, 13 sheets (Box 16)
  - Stamford, 84 sheets (Box 16)
  - Stamford (Main Street, "Gateway" Project), 1 sheet (Box 16)
  - Suffield, 14 sheets (Box 16)
  - Thomaston, 6 sheets (Box 16)
  - Torrington (Central City Neighborhoods), 8 sheets (Box 17)
  - Vernon (Includes Rockville), 21 sheets (Box 17)
  - Wallingford, 14 sheets (Box 17)
  - Waterbury (Downtown), 4 sheets (Box 17)
  - Westbrook, 7 sheets (Box 17)
  - West Haven, 8 sheets (Box 17)
  - Westport, 5 sheets (Box 17)
  - Westport (Saugatuck), 4 sheets (Box 17)
  - Winchester, 2 sheets (Box 17)
  - Windham (Downtown Willimantic), 3 sheets (Box 17)
  - Windham (Willimantic Residential Areas), 15 sheets (Box 17)
  - Windsor, 9 sheets (Box 17)
  - Woodbury, 6 sheets (Box 17)
  - United States Post Offices in Connecticut, 6 sheets (Box 17)